Most recent updates we've seen have been
incremental at best. There have been
some new models, some new feature drops,
lots of hype, but let's be honest, most
of what we've seen recently from Cloud
Code, from codecs, from Gemini, they've
been incremental improvements. Not much
real impact on how we actually build.
That is until Cursor dropped version two
last week, and I can tell you it has
already changed how I actually work. Two
features in particular have
fundamentally changed my day-to-day
workflow as a product builder. And I'm
not even talking about the new built-in
browser or the new voice mode and
cursor. And those are nice to have. But
two features that I'll focus on today
have had an observable meaningful shift
in my entire development workflow. So
the big headline that you may have heard
about cursor 2.0 are the new dual modes,
agent mode and editor mode. Now this UI
change alone wouldn't be revolutionary,
but it does perfectly capture the two
distinct ways that we actually work as
builders. At least it does for me. You
know, sometimes I need to delegate large
features and let agents cook on those
while I go work on something else or
take a break. And other times I want to
be hands-on, directing agents to make
specific changes while I sit here and
watch them work, and then I'll apply my
final polish. The new agent mode and
editor mode nail this paradigm. But
look, cursor has always been a code
editor with agent superpowers. And we've
already had ways to delegate autonomous
work to tools like codecs or cloud code
or even background agents in cursor. So
what's actually different about what
cursor 2.0 introduced and how is it
changing how we work? That's what we'll
get into in today's video. And if you're
new here, I'm Brian Castle. I help
professionals like you and me stay ahead
of the curve when it comes to building
with AI. And every Friday, I send out my
builder briefing. That's my five-minute
read to help you stay sharp. You can get
yours by going to buildermethods.com.
And subscribers are always the first to
know about my next live workshop where
we talk about what's working right now
when building with AI. So, here's how I
actually work. About half the time, I'm
hands-on with my codebase. And that
looks like a continuous cycle where I
give a prompt and then watch the agent
work and then I wait and then I prompt
again. But that waiting has added even
more friction than I realized because
even with how far today's models have
come and their competence with handling
complex multifile changes, it's that
waiting. It's that friction. It's real.
Because when I'm in the flow working
directly in my codebase, speed is
everything. And so in my view, the
killer new feature in Cursor 2.0 is much
larger than just a feature. Cursor
launched Composer 1. That's the first
large language model from the team at
Cursor. And calling this thing fast is
an understatement. It feels 20, 30, 50
times faster than any other model on the
market right now. You really have to
experience the speed to understand the
impact. Now, later in this video, I'll
show you a bigger build, but for now,
here's a taste. All right, so for now,
let's see what the new composer model in
cursor can do. I'll give it a pretty
small change. So, I've been working on
my buildermethods.com site, and uh one
thing that it's been missing is like a
true about page, you know. So, I've got
a lot of information about our free
resources and uh the Builder Methods Pro
membership and everything. I've got this
little letter here, but I wanted like a
dedicated about page that kind of speaks
to what this brand is all about and my
story behind it and everything. So, I
worked on writing that up over the
weekend. And here is the artifact that I
worked with Claude on creating. And I'm
pretty happy with this. I'll probably
edit it a little bit further, but you
know, this is a pretty good start for
what I want to put into like an about
page. So I'm going to just copy that and
let's go into I'm starting in agent mode
here. Notice over here I'm selecting
composer one that is cursors agentic
coding model. Yeah. So let's uh let's
give this a try. So and I also want to
link to it from the footer. It should
probably go in one of these. I'll just
add it under free resources for now.
Okay. So my prompt is pretty simple.
Like I want to add an about page. This
is the route. This is the controller I
want to use. I'm asking it to use the
same uh layout conventions that I've
used on other pages. I want to add a
link to it in the footer. And then here
is the content for this page. And so I
just pasted in the the markdown from uh
from the cloud artifact. All right. So
let's go ahead and uh kick this off.
So it's reading and it's going. Look at
look at this thing. Wow. Done. Wow. I
mean let's let's take a look. You know
what? I'm going to use the new built-in
browser. So I'm going to do uh command
shiftB. Oops. This is one thing that's
not so great about cursor so far. I'm
sure they're going to smooth this out.
Is like every time I use keyboard
shortcuts to change the panels, my
panels layout gets all out of whack. So,
I hope that that improves. So, anyway,
here we are. If I scroll down. Okay, so
here is my link to about. And yeah, it
looks uh looks pretty good. I I didn't
want to have my face there. And these
probably shouldn't be centered. All
right. So, not bad. I now one of the
really cool features of the new browser
feature is this select element. So I can
select an entire div and I can just
refer to it. So I want to make all
sections on the page the same width as
this div and it's just going to point to
that and it's sort of covered up there.
But you can see it sort of references
that that particular div. All right. So
I'm asking it to make a couple tweaks on
that. So you know I gave it a bunch of
tweaks that hit like multiple spots and
uh it's already done with them. the
content a little thinner. Uh, I'm going
to change the colors on this. I might
move this up into the hero, but I'll
handle that that like layout stuff a
little bit later. So, let's get on with
the video. Now, that was a simple
example, of course, but yesterday,
Composer refactored hundreds of lines in
my codebase, made perfect UI changes,
and it was done in under 20 seconds. And
later yesterday, I needed to add a
search feature across multiple models in
my app. Again, Composer knocked it out
in 20 seconds. One shot. Now, before
today, those are examples of tasks that
I would have spent time specking out and
delegating to an autonomous agent while
I go grab coffee or take a walk. But
now, given this new speed, I'm able to
pull those tasks into my more active
workflow when I'm sitting here crafting
my product. Now, what's really
interesting to me is that Cursor, a
tools company, is getting into the model
game. And I think that this could be the
start of a trend where toolm makers
develop purpose-built models that are
far superior at their job to be done.
And in the case of Curser releasing
their first LLM, Composer 1, it makes
perfect sense. They have unique training
data from their massive user base of
developers. And they can build a model
that's optimized for only one thing,
writing code really fast. And so Cursor
doesn't have to handle all the other use
cases that the models from OpenAI,
Anthropic, Google need to serve. And I
have to think that that's a big reason
why Cursor's Composer model is just
about as competent as Claude Sonnet 4.5,
but way faster. Now, like I said, only
about half my time is spent actually
looking at my codebase while my agents
are working on it. The rest of the time,
I want to give my agents a big new
feature to build and have them go off
and work autonomously while I work on
other things or call it a day and come
back in the morning. In Cursor 2.0,
agent mode isn't just a UI update. I
mean, it is, but it introduces something
that I think is an even bigger deal.
Now, we've had autonomous agents for
some time now. Cloud code led the way
when it pulled us away from our actual
code, and we started trusting our coding
agent to do more work on its own. Then
cursor launched background agents. Open
AAI launched codecs. And so we've been
trending into this era of letting agents
do the work while we interface with the
agents. But that only sticks if agents
can actually deliver on what we ask of
them. And that success rate is what
drives our own adoption and our team's
adoption of this more hands-off style of
working. The truth is, no matter how
great our specs are or how well we
prompt, the more complex the task is,
the more variation we see in the success
rate from our agents because we know
that we can give the same exact prompt
to the same exact model multiple times
and you can get very different results.
And so, Cursor 2.0 introduced parallel
agents and it solves this problem
beautifully. It's the easiest way to
give the same prompt to multiple agents
and have them work in parallel and then
compare their work and decide which one
is best. All right, so let's run a demo
where I'll show you how we can run
multiple agents in parallel to build out
the same thing. So for this demo, I am
in cursor 2.0. I'm in agent mode and
we're going to be building out a simple
weather app. I have prepared a a prompt.
I'm going to pop that in here. Now, now
since this is a new app and a bunch of
new features and it's, you know, not
super small. Now, when we're building
something that's like a medium to large
size build, I do like to start uh with a
plan. You know, uh spec driven
development. The whole value of that is
to make sure that the agents and our
plan are in full alignment. And that's
really important especially when we're
going to be spinning up multiple agents
because of course that's going to come
with some added costs and we don't want
to, you know, spin our wheels and waste
our time and waste our money on having
an incorrect plan from the outset. In
this case, we'll be using cursors plan
mode, which I I think has gotten
actually a lot better. I like it a lot.
So, I'm going to switch this to plan
mode. And of course, you could use
something like agent OS that does a
really good job of developing even more
in-depth specs and task lists. But
cursors, plan mode works works pretty
well. And I also find that sonnet 4.5 is
a little bit better at planning big bu
build builds and also uh asking really
uh smart clarifying questions. Composer
is okay with that but not quite as good
as sonnet. I think that's sort of the
case in general across the board. Sonnet
4.5 is still my go-to model for most
things but man that that speed from
composer is unreal. Okay, so we're going
to start with just one one single agent
creating a plan and then we'll get into
spinning up three agents to build out
the plan. Okay, so I'm going to answer
these uh clarifying questions. Okay, so
I'm just going to review this plan
before we get started. And again, this
is a really important step to make sure
that we're on the same page and that
we're going to give all three agents uh
the right instructions uh to kind of try
to set them up for success. We're going
to build this out on the homepage. We're
going to display some weather data.
We'll have a responsive layout. I think
this is looking good. And we have a
pretty simple uh to-do list that cursor
uh set up for us. Okay, so that is good.
Now, let's go ahead and start building
this. I'm going to start a new agent.
And so, now here is where we're going to
spin up multiple agents to build the
same thing. So, first of all, let's just
mention this this plan. I'll just say
build this. That's probably not even
necessary, but just sort of a habit. So,
I am referencing this plan in the prompt
itself. And then we're going to come
here and select the model and we'll go
to use multiple models. So this is how
we can start to uh spin up multiple
agents. As you can see, I have three
models checked here. We have one for
composer one. That is cursor's new
model. We're going to use that as one of
them. We'll use Sonnet 4.5. That's
really my go-to in general for for most
things. Uh, I still think it's just
slightly better in terms of quality and
capability than all the all the rest of
the models right now, but composer one
is just so much faster that that adds a
lot of value as well. And it's very
close in in quality in my experience so
far. And then in the third agent, we'll
try GPT5 codeex, which I also think is
pretty good, and I go to that sometimes.
Yeah. And also, you know, we have one X
set for each of these. I could go in
here and multiply it and have like two
different set 4.5s and and two composer
ones and every single agent is going to
have a slightly different uh result, a
different take on this prompt. That's
the nature of large language models. Uh
but they all will be working off of the
same plan and we're going to start them
off all at the same time and we're going
to see how they work uh side by side.
Let's go ahead and do that now. Okay. So
now we have uh this nice interface here.
You know, one, two, three. I can easily
tab between them. I do wish that cursor
would have a little bit better keyboard
navigation with these. I I hope that
that comes along because I like to have
everything available on the keyboard and
so far I haven't found an easy way to
bind these to a key mapping. Wow. I mean
composer one is is already actually
finished and uh in set 4.5 is still uh
zero of three to-dos. Looks like codeex
is sort of asking for permission to
proceed and I'm just going to say
proceed. Now, by the way, before we
start uh reviewing the code, let me just
show you exactly what's going on because
it could be really confusing when we're
using git work trees. Like where are all
these agents actually making edits to
which files and where do they actually
live on our system? So, to make this
clear, I always like to open up finder
and just sort of like get oriented with
what we're actually looking at here. So,
on the left side, I'm looking at my
actual project. That's we called it
weatheroo. And here is the rails app.
these files. If I go back in here and I
go into editor mode, these files right
here, that is the like the Rails
application that I've already spun up
for this project. But none of these
three agents actually have made any
edits on our core Rails app. So for
example, if I look at it in the browser
right now, I still see my default hello
world root page. So I'm not yet seeing
any of the work from any of the agents,
right? So where is that that work
actually being done? Well, if I open up
Finder again over here on the right
side, I go into my system level and then
I'll go into the cursor folder. That's a
hidden folder on your system. Then go
into work trees and then you'll see a
folder that was automatically created
matching the same name as the project.
In this case, it's weatheroo. And then
in there, I have three folders with
these sort of like random code names.
Each of these is a work tree. So, a git
work tree is a complete replica. It's a
complete copy of your entire codebase.
All the files, all the folders, they get
copied into their own respective folders
here. So each of these folders
corresponds to each of these agents. So
in agent mode, I can toggle between them
here. And that's exactly the same as in
editor mode. Now, running multiple
agents with git work trees isn't new.
And I did a video on this with Claude
Code months ago, but the process was
complicated, unintuitive, and I had to
whip up a script to make it easier. It
was kind of a pain. Cursor 2.0 makes it
simple. Multiple agents working
simultaneously on different branches all
managed through a clean interface. Okay,
so uh let's see how we did. So here is
how you can actually preview the work of
each of the individual agents and
compare the results one by one. So you
can do this in either mode, agent mode
or editor mode. Let's go into editor
mode here. And we can pick an agent.
Let's start with Sonnet 4.5. So it looks
like all three of them are complete now.
And again, by default, the main branch
is still showing our default uh hello
world page. So I'm going to go ahead and
apply all from the sonnet 4.5 agent. And
I can see that I have because now it
says reapply. So if I refresh here.
Okay, so we're getting a failed to fetch
location name and I'm seeing some some
errors in the console there. So, that's
an issue and maybe we'll we'll work
through that. But before we do, let's
see how the other agents did. Let's
undo. Now, what that did was it it sort
of pulled those changes back and now
we're back to our our original state.
So, now let's flip over to the middle
agent composer one. So, here let's apply
that. And this one's having trouble as
well. If we retry. Okay, so we're
getting some looks like some corores
errors. Okay, maybe third time is a
charm. Let's see uh how we did with uh
GPT5 codeex. I'm going to apply that
one. By the way, I I undid the composer
one first. Went over to GPT5 and I
applied that. And so now, okay, so this
is actually loading. Okay, so this is
actually working. This is um this is my
actual temperature and weather at my
current location. I see my next 24
hours. That's pretty good. I've got a
7-day forecast. I actually really like
the design. It's nice and clean. Let's
see how we did with like a mobile layout
if we collapse it down. Okay, not bad. I
don't love like the current location
coordinates. I'd like it to actually
show my city name. So, maybe that could
be like an edit that we would that we
would roll with. But GPT5 Codeex, I I
would not have guessed that that one had
the best first draft out of uh out of
these three. But you know what? I bet
it's something probably sort of simple
to fix these errors. So, let's go undo
that. Let's go back to the composer one
version and I will apply that one. So,
now we're back on this version which is
showing an error. Let's see if we can
get this working. So, I'm going to
screenshot all of this and I'm using
CleanShot for that on the Mac which I
love. Drop that in here and you know we
have the composer agent activated and uh
let's just you know give it that and see
if we can get this working. Okay. So,
there we go. Uh, it was able to to fix
that. So, now we have this is the
version from Composer 1, which is very
nice. I like it. Uh, a lot lighter.
[laughter] Um, this one is actually
showing my town. I live here in in
Orange, Connecticut. This is uh the
weather here. This is the 24hour
forecast. I've got my 7-day forecast.
Let's see how we did on the responsive
layout. Okay, not bad. Yeah, that works.
I didn't ask it to do a dark mode, but
let's see if it handled that. No, it did
not. Okay. Yeah. Uh it, you know, it
basically built everything that I wanted
it. Okay. So, now over on Sonnet, I
actually did uh have it, you know, fix
the error there and uh I reloaded and
now Sonnet 4.5. This is what it came up
with. This is now working. Although, I
must say I'm not as happy with the
overall design. And it has that very
typical sort of vibe coded, you know,
big rounded corners, lots of drop
shadows kind of kind of vibe. So, uh,
yeah, but it it does work. It's got the
weather. It's got my my hourly forecast.
7-day. Let's see. Refresh weather. Nice
little loading animation. It doesn't
have my actual location name, so that's
probably something that could be fixed.
Yeah. So, I reapplied the composer
agents work, and I think I like this the
best. It has all the functionality that
I would need. Although I must say I did
like the design work from the GPT5
codeex one. So that was pretty nice. My
next step at this stage would be to
choose one and then keep working off of
that. So for example, I think that this
one with composer one actually ended up
being, you know, like the the best one
to work with. You know, just as an
example, my next step might be to add
like a dark mode. So let's go ahead and
see if it can uh see if it can do that.
Please automatically support both light
mode and dark mode. and include a toggle
switch at the top for the user to switch
between them.
I'm just having so much fun watching the
composer one agent work. I mean, just
look at how fast it is actually
implementing these changes. It's
unbelievable to me.
Done. Okay, so we have our little uh
switcher up there. Nice. We've got dark
mode and light mode. That works. I like
it. Now, running parallel agents
multiplies your costs, of course, and
that's why I tend to be more selective
in using this feature. I use it for more
complex critical builds where the
productivity gain justifies the costs.
So, the team at Cursor clearly
understands our two different modes of
working and they built that right into
their product, which I love. So, I
really do think that this Cursor 2.0
update represents a real turning point
in how we build. And it's been quite a
year when it comes to how our workflow
as builders keeps evolving. And you
know, specdriven development is one of
those new paradigms that I've talked a
lot about on this channel, and I think
it's still relevant, especially in agent
mode in cursor 2.0. So, if you're not
familiar with spec driven development,
then I want you to see my other video on
how spec driven development works in the
real world. But before you head there,
hit subscribe so you don't miss my next
video on building with AI. So, thanks
for watching. Let me know what you think
and I'll see you over there next. Let's
keep building.